♫ Jill Sobule: At a conference in Monterey by the big, big jellyfish tank, ♫
♫في مؤتمر في مونتيري .. بالقرب من خزان القناديل الكبير ♫
♫ I first saw you and I got so shy. ♫
♫رأيتك للمرة الأولى .. وقد أصبت بالخجل ♫
♫ You see, I was a little paranoid 'cause I might have been high. ♫
♫لقد كنت قلقة بعض الشيء لانني كنت منتشية بالكحول ♫
♫ And I hadn't done that in ages and I won't do that again. ♫
♫ولم أكن قد قمت بهذا منذ مدة طويلة ولن أقوم به مرة أخرى ♫
♫ But that's another story. ♫
♫ولكن هذه قصة أخرى ♫
♫ Loved you forever and I've been a big fan, ♫
♫لقد احببت مذ حييت وكنت من أشد المعجبين ♫
♫ the one-woman shows, I even rented "Pat." ♫
♫برنامج المرأة الواحدة .. لدرجة أنني إستأجرت " بات " ♫
♫ I got enough nerve to come up to you, ♫
♫لقد تشجعت وجئت إليك ♫
♫ but little did I know one year later we'd be doing this show. ♫
♫ولوهلة شعرت أنه بعد عام واحد سنقوم بهذا العرض سويةً♫
♫ I sing. Julia Sweeney: I tell stories. Together: The Jill and Julia Show. ♫
♫أنا أغني .... أنا أخبر القصص .... عرض جيل وجوليا♫
♫ Sobule: Sometimes it works. Sweeney: Sometimes it doesn't. ♫
♫جيل سوبلو : أحيانا تنجح الامور ... وأحيانا لا ♫
♫ Together: The Jill and Julia Show. ♫
♫عرض جيل وجوليا♫
♫ Sweeney: At a conference in Monterey next to the big, big jellyfish tank, ♫
♫جوليا سويندي:في مؤتمر في مونتري .. بالقرب من خزان للقناديل ♫
♫ I first saw you and I wasn't so shy. ♫
♫رأيتك للمرة الأولى وقد أصبت بالخجل ♫
I made a beeline for you and told you what a huge fan I was
لقد جئتك مباشرة وقلت لك أنني معجبة كبيرة بك
ever since I was writing that pilot for Fox, and Wendy
♫مذ ذلك الحين وأنا اكتب عن الطيران ل محطة فوكس .. و لويندي ♫
and I wanted you to do the theme song.
♫وكنت أريد أن أقوم بأغنية شارة للبرنامج♫
And then the pilot didn't go and I was so sad,
♫ولكن الطيار لم يعرض وقد حزنت ♫
but I kept remaining a fan of yours.
♫ولكنني بقيت من اشد المعجبين بك ♫
And then when I went through that big, horrible breakup with Carl
♫ومن ثم عندما .. واجهت ذلك الانفصال الشنيع مع كارل ♫
and I couldn't get off the couch, I listened to your song,
♫ولم أستطع بعده القيام من الأريكة .. وأستمعت لأغنيتك ♫
♫ "Now That I Don't Have You," ♫ over and over and over and over again.
♫الان لم تعد معي ♫ مرة تلو المرة ومرة تلو المرة
And I can't believe you're here and that I'm meeting you here at TED.
ولم أكن أصدق أنك هنا .. وسوف أقابلك في " تيد "
And also, I can't believe that we're eating sushi
ولم أصدق أيضاً أننا سنأكل السوشي معا ً
in front of the fish tank,
أمام حوض السمك
which, personally, I think is really inappropriate.
والذي أظنه فعلا أمرٌ غير لائق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And little did I know that one year later ... ♫ we'd be doing this show. ♫
ولوهلة شعرت أنه بعد عام واحد ♫سنقوم بهذا العرض سويةً♫
♫ Sobule: I sing. Sweeney: I tell stories. Together: The Jill and Julia Show. ♫
♫جيل سوبلو :أنا أُغني ... أنا اقص القصص ... عرض جيل وجوليا♫
Sobule: Hey, they asked us back! Sweeney: Can you stand it?!
جيل سوبلو : هيه .. لقد طلبوا منا العودة ... هل يمكنك تصديق هذا ؟
♫ Together: The Jill and Julia, the Jill and Julia, the Jill and Julia Show. ♫
♫عرض جيل وجوليا .. جيل وجوليا ... جيل وجوليا♫
♫ Sobule: Why are all our heroes so imperfect? ♫
♫جيل سوبلو : لماذا ليس كل ابطالنا كاملون ♫
♫ Why do they always bring me down? ♫
♫لماذا دوما يحبطونا ♫
♫ Why are all our heroes so imperfect? ♫
♫لماذا ليس كل ابطالنا كاملون ♫
♫ Statue in the park has lost his crown. ♫
♫إن التمثال في الحديقة قد فقد تاجه ♫
♫ William Faulkner, drunk and depressed. ♫ Sweeney: Mmm.
♫ويليم فانلكنير .. سكير و محبط ♫
♫ Dorothy Parker, mean, drunk and depressed. ♫ Sweeney: I know.
♫دورثي باركر شرير , سكير ومحبط ♫
♫ And that guy, "Seven Years in Tibet," turned out to be a Nazi. ♫ Sweeney: Yeah.
♫وذلك الشاب .. سبة سنوات في التيبت .. من ثم تبين انه نازي ♫
♫ Founding fathers all had slaves. ♫ Sweeney: I know.
♫الآباء المؤسسون كلهم كانوا يملكون العبيد ♫
♫ The explorers slaughtered the braves. ♫ Sweeney: Horribly.
♫ المستكشفون ذبحوا الشجعان.♫ سويني: بفظاعة.
♫ Sobule: The Old Testament God can be so petty. ♫
♫جيل سوبلو : العهد القديم .. هل يمكن ان يكون الإله بهذه القسوة♫
Sweeney: Don't get me started on that. (Laughter)
♫جوليا سويندي: ولا تدعوني أكمل في هذا ♫
♫ Sobule: Paul McCartney, jealous of John, even more so now that he's gone. ♫
♫جيل سوبلو : بول ماكارثي يغار من جون .. وحتى بعد ان توفي ♫
♫ Dylan was so mean to Donovan in that movie. ♫
♫وبوب ديلان كان قاسيا جدا مع دونفان في ذلك الفلم ♫
♫ Pablo Picasso, cruel to his wives. ♫ Sweeney: Horrible.
♫بابلو بيكاسو كان وقحا مع زوجاته ♫ شنيع
♫ Sobule: My favorite poets took their own lives. ♫
♫جيل سوبلو : شعرائي المفضلين إنتحروا ♫
♫ Orson Welles peaked at twenty-five, below before our eyes. ♫
♫اورسون ويلز ... ♫
♫ And he sold bad wine. ♫
♫وهو يبيع خمر فاسد ♫
♫ Together: Why are all our heroes so imperfect? Yeah ♫
♫سوياً: لماذا كل أبطالنا ليسوا كاملين، يااه؟ ♫
♫ Why do they always bring me down? ♫
♫لماذا دوما يحبطونا ♫
♫ Sobule: Heard Babe Ruth was full of malice. ♫ Sweeney: Oh.
♫وقد كان هيرد بابي روث مليء بالخبث♫
♫ Lewis Carroll I'm sure did Alice. ♫ Sweeney: What?!
♫ أما عن لويس كارول فأنا متأكدة أنه شاذ ♫
♫ Plato in the cave with those very young boys. ♫ Sweeney: Ooh...
♫وقد كان افلاطون في الكهف مع الشباب الصغار ♫ أوووه
♫ Sobule: Hillary supported the war. ♫
♫جيل سوبلو :وقد دعمت هيلاري كيلنتون الحرب ♫
♫ Sweeney: Even Thomas Friedman supported the war. ♫ (Laughter)
♫جوليا سويندي: وحتى توماس فريدمان دعم الحرب ♫
♫ Sobule: Colin Powell turned out to be ... Together: ... such a pussy. ♫ (Laughter) (Applause)
♫جيل سوبلو :وقد تبين أن كولن باول هو مجرد ... جبان ♫
♫ Sobule: William Faulkner, drunk and depressed, ♫
♫جيل سوبلو :ويليم فالكنر سكير ومحبط ♫
♫ Tennessee Williams, drunk and depressed. ♫ Sweeney: Yeah.
♫تينيسي ويليمز سكير ومحبط ♫
♫ Sobule: Take it, Julia. ♫
جيل سوبلو :خذي الزمام جوليا
Sweeney: Okay. Oprah was never necessarily a big hero of mine.
جوليا سويندي: حسناً .. لم تكن أوبرا أحد أبطالي الكبار بالضرورة ..
I mean, I watch Oprah mostly when I'm home in Spokane
أعني أني كنت اتابع أوبرا عندما كنت في المنزل في سبوكان
visiting my mother. And to my mother,
أزور والدتي .. ولوالدتي
Oprah is a greater moral authority than the Pope,
أوبرا هي مثال رائع للأخلاق أكثر من البابا نفسه
which is actually saying something because she's a devout Catholic.
وهو شيء تقوله رغم انها كاثوليكية ورعة
Anyway, I like Oprah -- I like her girlfriendy-ness,
بصورة ما .. أنا احب أوبرا .. وأحب صديقتها نيس
I like her weight issues,
وأحب مشاكلها مع الوزن
I like how she's transformed talk television,
وأحب كيف حولت البرامج الحوارية على التلفاز
I like how she's brought reading back to America --
وأحب كيف أعادت القراءة إلى امريكا
but there was something that happened the last two weeks
ولكن هنالك شيء حدث في الاسبوعين الاخيرين
that was ... I call it the Soon-Yi moment:
والذي أدعوه - لحظة " ياي - القريبة " -
it is the moment when I cannot continue supporting someone.
وهي تلك اللحظة التي أعجز بعدها عن الاستمرار بدعم أحد
And that was that she did two entire shows
وتلك اللحظة عندما قامة أوبرا بعمل برنامجين كاملين ...
promoting that movie "The Secret."
للترويج لفلم السيكرت
Do you guys know about that movie "The Secret"?
هل تعلمون يا شباب فلم " السيكرت "
It makes "What the Bleep Do We Know" seem like a doctoral dissertation
إنه الذي يجعل فلم " What the Bleep Do We Know " يبدو وكأنه إطروحة دكتوراة
from Harvard on quantum mechanics -- that's how bad it is.
من هارفرد عن ميكانيك الكم .. إنه بهذا السوء
It makes "The DaVinci Code" seem like "War and Peace."
إنه يجعل فلم " شيفرة دافنشي " تبدو وكأنها عن الحرب والسلام
That movie is so horrible. It promotes such awful pseudoscience.
ذلك الفلم السيء والذي يروج للعلم الخرافي السيء
And the basic idea is
والفكرة الاساسية كانت ..
that there's this law of attraction, and
انه يوجد ما يدعى قانون الجذب ..
your thoughts have this vibrating energy
وأن أفكارك تملك هذه الطاقة النابضة
that goes out into the universe
والتي تنطلق إلى الكون
and then you attract good things to happen to you.
ومن ثم تجذب الاشياء الجيدة التي تحصل لك
On a scientific basis, it's more than just "Power of Positive Thinking" --
وعلى الجانب العلمي .. إنها أكثر من فقط " قوة التفكير الإيجابي "
it has a horrible, horrible dark side. Like if you get ill,
فهذا الفلم له جانب سيء ومظلم جداً جداً .. وهو كما وكأنك ستصاب بالمرض إن آمنت به
it's because you've just been thinking negative thoughts.
لانه يعني أنك كنت تفكر بالأفكار السلبية طيلة الوقت
Yeah, stuff like that was in the movie and she's promoting it.
نعم أشياء سيئة كهذه في الفلم ... وهي تروج له
And all I'm saying is that I really wish that Murray Gell-Mann
وكل ما أقوله أنني اتمنى من " موري جيلمان " ..
would go on Oprah
أن تذهب إلى أوبرا
and just explain to her that the law of attraction is, in fact, not a law.
وتشرح لها أن " قانون الجذب " في الحقيقة ليس قانوناً
So that's what I have to say.
هذا كل ما أريد أن أقوله
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
♫ Sobule: I sing. Sweeney: I tell stories. Together: The Jill and Julia Show. ♫
♫أنا أغني .. أنا أقص القصص .. عرض جيل وجوليا ♫
♫ Sobule: Sometimes it works. Sweeney: Sometimes it doesn't. ♫
♫جيل سوبلو : أحيانا ينجح وأحيانا لا ♫
♫ Together: The Jill and Julia, the Jill and Julia, the Jill and Julia Show. ♫
♫عرض جيل وجوليا .. عرض جيل وجوليا ... عرض جيل وجوليا♫
(Applause)
(تصفيق)